function showAnswer(){
    var e = document.getElementById("answer");
    var w=document.getElementById("show");
    
    if(e.style.display == 'none'){
        e.style.display = 'block';
        w.innerHTML ="Hide Answer";
    }else{
        e.style.display = 'none';
        w.innerHTML ="Show Answer";
    }
}

var ruth = { //might need to add "james" : [] but dont have to cause chapters are definet numbers
    "c1":[
        {"question":"According to Ruth 1:1, At what time in Israel's history does this story take place?","answer":"Now it came to pass, in the days when the judges ruled,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:1, Why did Elimelech and Naomi and their family move to the country of Moab?","answer":"that there was a famine in the land."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:1, From what city and territory did Elimelech come? (2 points)","answer":"Bethlehem, Judah"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:1, Who went to Moab from Bethlehem, Judah, in the days of the Judges, because of a famine?","answer":"he and his wife and his two sons."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:1, How many people were in Naomi and Elimelech's family?","answer":"he and his wife and his two sons."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:1, How many sons did Namo and Elimelech have?","answer":"he and his wife and his two sons."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:2, What was Naomi's husband's name?","answer":"The name of the man was Elimelech,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:2, Who was Elimelech's wife?","answer":"the name of his wife was Naomi,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:2, Who was Chilion's brother?","answer":"and the names of his two sons were Mahlon"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:2, Who was Mahlon's brother?","answer":"and Chilion\u2014"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:2, Elimelech belonged to what group in Bethlehem, Judah?","answer":"Ephrathites"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:2, From what city were Elimelech and Naomi?","answer":"Bethlehem"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:2, From what tribe of the children of Israel were Elimelech and his family?","answer":"Judah."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:2, To what country did Elimelech and his family go?","answer":"And they went to the country of Moab and remained there."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:3, Who died?","answer":"Then Elimelech, Naomi\u2019s husband, died;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:3, How was Elimelech related to Naomi?","answer":"Then Elimelech, Naomi\u2019s husband, died;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:3, After Elimelech died, who was left? (3 points)","answer":"Naomi, and her two sons"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:3, how many sons did Naomi have?","answer":"and her two sons."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:4, What did Naomi's sons do after their father died?","answer":"Now they took wives of the women of Moab:"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:4, From what country did Naomi's sons take wives?","answer":"Now they took wives of the women of Moab:"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:4, What was the name of Naomi's daughter-in-law, besides Ruth?","answer":"the name of the one was Orpah,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:4, What was the name of Naomi's daughter-in-law, besides Orpah?","answer":"and the name of the other Ruth."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:4, How long were Naomi's boys married in Moab?","answer":"And they dwelt there about ten years."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:5, Who also died? (2 points)","answer":"Then both Mahlon and Chilion also died;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:5, What happened to Mahlon and Chilion?","answer":"Then both Mahlon and Chilion also died;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:5, Who was the only person left of the family?","answer":"so the woman survived her two sons and her husband."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:6, What did Naomi do after her husband and sons died?","answer":"Then she arose with her daughters-in-law"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:6, How many of Naomi's daughters-in-law started packing to go with Naomi back to Israel?","answer":"Then she arose with her daughters-in-law"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:6, From what country was Naomi going to return to Israel, after her husband and sons died?","answer":"that she might return from the country of Moab,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:6, What had Naomi heard God had done while she was in Moab?","answer":"for she had heard in the country of Moab that the Lord had visited His people"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:6, What had God given His people, while Naomi was in Moab?","answer":"by giving them bread."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:7, What did Naomi do after she heard that there was bread in Israel?","answer":"Therefore she went out from the place where she was,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:7, Who went with Naomi out of the city where she was?","answer":"and her two daughters-in-law with her;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:7, How many of Naomi's daughters-in-law started going with her back to Israel?","answer":"and her two daughters-in-law with her;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:7, Where did Naomi and the two daughters-in-law start going?","answer":"and they went on the way to return to the land of Judah."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:8, Who told the daughters-in-law to go back to her mother's house?","answer":"And Naomi said to her two daughters-in-law,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:8, To whom did Naomi tell to go back to her mother's house?","answer":"And Naomi said to her two daughters-in-law,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:8, Where did Naomi tell her two daughters-in-law to go?","answer":"\u201cGo, return each to her mother\u2019s house."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:8, What did Naomi ask the Lord to do for her two daughters-in-law?","answer":"The Lord deal kindly with you,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:8, Why did Naomi ask the Lord to be kind to her two daughters-in-law?","answer":"as you have dealt with the dead and with me."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:9, What did Naomi want God to give her two daughters-in-law, each in the house of her husband?","answer":"The Lord grant that you may find rest,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:9, What did Naomi want her two daughers-in-law to go back and do?","answer":"each in the house of her husband.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:9, Where did Naomi want her two daughters-in-law to find rest?","answer":"each in the house of her husband.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:9, How did Naomi tell her daughters-in-law goodbye?","answer":"So she kissed them,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:9, What was the reaction of the two girls? (2 points)","answer":"and they lifted up their voices and wept."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:10, What did both daughters-in-law say to Naomi, after she suggested they go back to their country to get remarried?","answer":"And they said to her, \u201cSurely we will return with you to your people.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:11, What did Naomi advise the two girls to do?","answer":"But Naomi said, \u201cTurn back, my daughters;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:11, After she tells the girls to go back, what question does Naomi ask her two daughters-in-law why they will do what?","answer":"why will you go with me?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:11, Naomi asked if she had what still in her womb?","answer":"Are there still sons in my womb,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:11, Naomi asked if she had sons where?","answer":"Are there still sons in my womb,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:11, What would any more sons of Naomi become to the two girls?","answer":"that they may be your husbands?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:12, What did Naomi tell the girls to do, because she was too old to have a husband.","answer":"Turn back, my daughters,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:12, Ruth said she was too old to have what?","answer":"go\u2014for I am too old to have a husband."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:12, If Naomi had hope, what was she hoping for?","answer":"If I should say I have hope, if I should have a husband tonight"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:12, If Naomi was not too old to have a husband, what might she do?","answer":"and should also bear sons,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:13, Naomi asked the girls if they would wait until what happened?","answer":"would you wait for them till they were grown?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:13, When Naomi explained it would take a long time for any sons she would have to grow up, what question did she ask the girls?","answer":"Would you restrain yourselves from having husbands?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:13, What grieved Naomi?","answer":"No, my daughters; for it grieves me very much for your sakes that the hand of the Lord has gone out against me!\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:14, After Naomi pointed out the girls would be waiting a long time for husbands, what did they do?","answer":"Then they lifted up their voices and wept again;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:14, Which girl left Naomi to go back home?","answer":"and Orpah kissed her mother-in-law,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:14, How did Orphah say goodbye?","answer":"and Orpah kissed her mother-in-law,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:14, Orphah left, but what did Ruth do?","answer":"but Ruth clung to her."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:15, Naomi said Ruth's sister-in-law had gone back to what two things? (2 points)","answer":"And she said, \u201cLook, your sister-in-law has gone back to her people and to her gods;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:15, How were Ruth and Orphah related?","answer":"And she said, \u201cLook, your sister-in-law has gone back to her people and to her gods;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:15, After Orphah left, What did Naomi encourage Ruth to do?","answer":"return after your sister-in-law.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:16, What two similar things did Ruth ask Naomi not to do? (2 points)","answer":"But Ruth said: \u201cEntreat me not to leave you, Or to turn back from following after you;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:16, Ruth said she would go where?","answer":"For wherever you go, I will go;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:16, Ruth said wherever Naomi would go, what?","answer":"For wherever you go, I will go;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:16, Ruth said she would lodge where?","answer":"And wherever you lodge, I will lodge;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:16, Ruth said wherever Naomi would lodge, what?","answer":"And wherever you lodge, I will lodge;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:16, Ruth said Naomi's people would be what?","answer":"Your people shall be my people,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:16, Ruth said her people would be whom?","answer":"Your people shall be my people,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:16, Ruth said Naomi's God would be what?","answer":"And your God, my God."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:16, Ruth said her God would be whom?","answer":"And your God, my God."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:17, Where did Ruth say she would die?","answer":"Where you die, I will die,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:17, Where Naomi died, where would Ruth say she would die?","answer":"Where you die, I will die,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:17, Where did Ruth say she would be buried?","answer":"And there will I be buried."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:17, Where Naomi was buried?, and where did Ruth say she would be buried?","answer":"And there will I be buried."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:17, What did Ruth promise to Naomi about the rest of her life?","answer":"The Lord do so to me, and more also, If anything but death parts you and me.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:18, When did Naomi stop asking Ruth to go back home?","answer":"When she saw that she was determined to go with her,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:18, When Naomi saw that Ruth was determined to go with her, what did she do?","answer":"she stopped speaking to her."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:19, Ruth and Naomi kept walking until they got to what city?","answer":"Now the two of them went until they came to Bethlehem."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:19, what was the reaction of the people from Bethlehem when they saw Naomi?","answer":"And it happened, when they had come to Bethlehem, that all the city was excited because of them;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:19, True or False?  The people of Bethlehem didn't remember Naomi when she and Ruth arrived.","answer":"False."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:20, Yes or No?  Did Naomi want to have her name changed?","answer":"But she said to them, \u201cDo not call me Naomi;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:20, What did Naomi want everyone in Bethlehem to call her, instead of Naomi?","answer":"call me Mara,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:20, Why did Naomi want the people to call her Marah now?","answer":"for the Almighty has dealt very bitterly with me."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:21, Naomi said she had gone out of Bethlehem in what state?","answer":"I went out full,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:21, Naomi said she had gone out full, and come home how?","answer":"and the Lord has brought me home again empty."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:21, What did Naomi say the Lord had done against her?","answer":"Why do you call me Naomi, since the Lord has testified against me,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:21, What did Naomi say the Almighty had done to her?","answer":"and the Almighty has afflicted me?\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:22, Who went with Ruth back to Bethlehem?","answer":"So Naomi returned,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:22, Who came back to Bethlehem with Naomi?","answer":"and Ruth the Moabitess her daughter-in-law with her,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:22, From what country had Naomi and Ruth just come?","answer":"who returned from the country of Moab."},{"question":"According to Ruth 1:22, What time of year was it?","answer":"Now they came to Bethlehem at the beginning of barley harvest."}
        /*
        //
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        */
    ],

    "c2":[
        {"question":"According to Ruth 2:1, Describe Boaz' economic status.","answer":"a man of great wealth,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:1, Was Boaz related to Naomi through her side, or her husband's side?","answer":"of the family of Elimelech."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:1, What was the name of the wealthy relative of Elimelech?","answer":"His name was Boaz."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:2, What did Ruth ask Naomi if she could do?","answer":"So Ruth the Moabitess said to Naomi, \u201cPlease let me go to the field, and glean heads of grain after him in whose sight I may find favor.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:2, What was Naomi's response, when Ruth asked if she could go and glean in a field that day?","answer":"And she said to her, \u201cGo, my daughter.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:3, True or false?  Gleaning takes place after the reapers have gone through the field?","answer":"Then she left, and went and gleaned in the field after the reapers."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:3, True or false?  Gleaning takes place before the reapers have gone through the field?","answer":"Then she left, and went and gleaned in the field after the reapers."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:3, Ruth started gleaning in the field that belonged to whom?","answer":"And she happened to come to the part of the field belonging to Boaz,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:3, Boaz belonged to what family?","answer":"who was of the family of Elimelech."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:4, Who came from Bethlehem to check on his field and workers?","answer":"Now behold, Boaz came from Bethlehem,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:4, Boaz came to the field from what city?","answer":"Now behold, Boaz came from Bethlehem,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:4, How did Boaz greet the workers in his field?","answer":"and said to the reapers, \u201cThe Lord be with you!\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:4, How did the reapers return Boaz' greeting?","answer":"And they answered him, \u201cThe Lord bless you!\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:5, Whom did Boaz ask, when he saw Ruth in the field gleaning, and wanted to know who she was?","answer":"Then Boaz said to his servant who was in charge of the reapers,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:5, What did Boaz ask the servant who was in charge of the reapers?","answer":"\u201cWhose young woman is this?\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:6, Who told Boaz that this young woman was the girl who came back with Naomi from the country of Moab?","answer":"So the servant who was in charge of the reapers answered and said,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:6, Whom did the servant in charge of the reapers tell Boaz this girl was?","answer":"\u201cIt is the young Moabite woman who came back with Naomi from the country of Moab."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:7, What had Ruth asked the foreman of the reapers that morning?","answer":"And she said, \u2018Please let me glean and gather after the reapers among the sheaves.\u2019"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:7, How long had Ruth been working in the field?","answer":"So she came and has continued from morning until now,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:7, Besides working in the field, what else had Ruth done that day?","answer":"though she rested a little in the house.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:7, True or False?  Ruth had not rested at all that first day of gleaning?","answer":"though she rested a little in the house.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:7, True or False?  Ruth rested a little in the house that first day of gleaning?","answer":"though she rested a little in the house.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:8, How did Boaz get Ruth's attention, and start talking to her?","answer":"Then Boaz said to Ruth, \u201cYou will listen, my daughter, will you not?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:8, Where did Boaz tell Ruth NOT to glean?","answer":"Do not go to glean in another field,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:8, Boaz told Ruth not to go glean in another field, or do what?","answer":"nor go from here,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:8, Where did Boaz say Ruth should glean?","answer":"but stay close by my young women."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:9, Boaz told Ruth to glean in which field?","answer":"Let your eyes be on the field which they reap, and go after them."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:9, What had Boaz commanded his young men, concerning Ruth?","answer":"Have I not commanded the young men not to touch you?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:9, Whom had Boaz commanded not to touch Ruth?","answer":"Have I not commanded the young men not to touch you?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:9, What did Boaz say Ruth could do when she was thirsty?","answer":"And when you are thirsty, go to the vessels and drink from what the young men have drawn.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:10, What was Ruth's reaction to Boaz telling her she could glean in his fields, and drink water when she was thirsty? (2 points)","answer":"So she fell on her face, bowed down to the ground, and said to him,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:10, What did Ruth ask Boaz, after he said she could glean in his fields, and drink water when she was thirsty?","answer":"\u201cWhy have I found favor in your eyes, that you should take notice of me, since I am a foreigner?\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:11, Who told Ruth he had heard all that she had done for her mother-in-law since the death of her husband, and how she had left her father and mother and come to a land where she didn't know anybody?","answer":"And Boaz answered and said to her,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:11, What had Boaz heard about Ruth, concerning Naomi?","answer":"\u201cIt has been fully reported to me, all that you have done for your mother-in-law since the death of your husband,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:11, Boaz said he had heard all the things Ruth had done for her mother-in-law after the death of her husband, and what else, besides also coming to a people she did not know before?","answer":"and how you have left your father and your mother and the land of your birth,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:11, Boaz also said he knew Ruth had come to what kind of people, after she left her father and mother?","answer":"and have come to a people whom you did not know before."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:12, Whom did Boaz say would repay Ruth's work, for taking care of Naomi?","answer":"The Lord repay your work,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:12, What did Boaz say the Lord would do for Ruth?","answer":"The Lord repay your work,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:12, How much of a reward was Boaz asking God to give Ruth?","answer":"and a full reward be given you by the Lord God of Israel, under whose wings you have come for refuge.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:12, Where had Ruth come for refuge?","answer":"and a full reward be given you by the Lord God of Israel, under whose wings you have come for refuge.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:13, Ruth asked Boaz for what, because he had comforted her and spoken kindly to her, even though she was not like his maidservants?","answer":"Then she said, \u201cLet me find favor in your sight, my lord;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:13, Ruth thanked Boaz for what two things he had done, even though she was not like his handmaidens?","answer":"for you have comforted me, and have spoken kindly to your maidservant,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:13, Ruth was thankful for Boaz speaking kindly to her, even though she was what?","answer":"though I am not like one of your maidservants.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:14, What did Boaz serve for dinner for the reapers?","answer":"Now Boaz said to her at mealtime, \u201cCome here, and eat of the bread, and dip your piece of bread in the vinegar.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:14, When it was mealtime, what did Boaz tell Ruth?","answer":"Now Boaz said to her at mealtime, \u201cCome here, and eat of the bread, and dip your piece of bread in the vinegar.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:14, Beside whom did Ruth sit at mealtime?","answer":"So she sat beside the reapers,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:14, Besides bread and vinegar, what else did Boaz serve the reapers for lunch?","answer":"and he passed parched grain to her;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:14, Yes or No, Did Ruth get enough to eat for lunch?","answer":"and she ate and was satisfied,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:14, Yes or no? After Ruth was full from lunch, did she have any leftovers?","answer":"and kept some back."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:15, When did Boaz tell his men to let Ruth glean even among the sheaves, and not to reproach her?","answer":"And when she rose up to glean,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:15, Whom did Boaz tell to let Ruth glean even among the sheaves, and do not reproach her?","answer":"Boaz commanded his young men, saying,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:15, What added bonus did Boaz let Ruth do, besides just gleaning what the reapers had left?","answer":"\u201cLet her glean even among the sheaves, and do not reproach her."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:16, What did Boaz say the reapers should do purposely for Ruth?","answer":"Also let grain from the bundles fall purposely for her;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:16, Why were the reapers supposed to purposely let grain fall?","answer":"leave it that she may glean,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:16, Boaz said the reapers were to leave grain purposely for her, and not do what?","answer":"and do not rebuke her.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:17, When did Ruth stop gleaning in the field?","answer":"So she gleaned in the field until evening,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:17, What did Ruth do after she had stopped gleaning in the field that evening?","answer":"and beat out what she had gleaned,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:17, How much grain had Ruth gleaned that day?","answer":"and it was about an ephah of barley."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:18, After Ruth beat out the grain, where did she go?","answer":"Then she took it up and went into the city,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:18, What did Ruth show her mother-in-law?","answer":"and her mother-in-law saw what she had gleaned."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:18, What did Ruth give to her mother-in-law after she showed her all the grain she had gleaned for the day?","answer":"So she brought out and gave to her what she had kept back after she had been satisfied."},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:19, What two similar questions did Naomi ask Ruth, after she saw the pile of grain?","answer":"And her mother-in-law said to her, \u201cWhere have you gleaned today? And where did you work?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:19, Naomi asked a blessing upon whom?","answer":"Blessed be the one who took notice of you.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:19, What was the name of the man who let Ruth glean his field?","answer":"So she told her mother-in-law with whom she had worked, and said, \u201cThe man\u2019s name with whom I worked today is Boaz.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:20, Naomi was thankful for Boaz' kindness to whom?","answer":"Then Naomi said to her daughter-in-law, \u201cBlessed be he of the Lord, who has not forsaken His kindness to the living and the dead!\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:20, What surprising fact did Naomi tell Ruth about Boaz?","answer":"And Naomi said to her, \u201cThis man is a relation of ours, one of our close relatives.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:21, What did Ruth tell Naomi that Boaz had told her about how long she could glean in his field?","answer":"Ruth the Moabitess said, \u201cHe also said to me, \u2018You shall stay close by my young men until they have finished all my harvest.\u2019 \u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:22, With whom did Naomi say it would be good for Ruth to glean?","answer":"And Naomi said to Ruth her daughter-in-law, \u201cIt is good, my daughter, that you go out with his young women,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:22, Naomi said it would be good if people don't meet Ruth where?","answer":"and that people do not meet you in any other field.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:23, With whom did Ruth glean during the barley harvest and wheat harvest?","answer":"So she stayed close by the young women of Boaz,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:23, Through what two harvests did Ruth glean in Boaz' field?","answer":"to glean until the end of barley harvest and wheat harvest;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 2:23, With whom did Ruth live?","answer":"and she dwelt with her mother-in-law."}
        /*
        //
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        */
    ],

    "c3":[
        {"question":"According to Ruth 3:1, What is Naomi going to seek for Ruth?","answer":"Then Naomi her mother-in-law said to her, \u201cMy daughter, shall I not seek security for you, that it may be well with you?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:2, Naomi reminded Ruth that who was their relative?","answer":"Now Boaz, whose young women you were with, is he not our relative?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:2, Naomi reminded Ruth what about Boaz?","answer":"Now Boaz, whose young women you were with, is he not our relative?"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:2, What did Naomi say Boaz was going to do that night?","answer":"In fact, he is winnowing barley tonight at the threshing floor."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:3, What two things did Naomi tell Ruth to do before putting on her best garment that night? (2 points)","answer":"Therefore wash yourself and anoint yourself,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:3, After Ruth took a bath and put on some perfume, then what two things was she supposed to do? (2 points)","answer":"put on your best garment and go down to the threshing floor;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:3, When did Naomi tell Ruth to make herself known to Boaz?  After he had done what two things? (2 points)","answer":"but do not make yourself known to the man until he has finished eating and drinking."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:4, What was Ruth supposed to do before she uncovered Boaz' feet that night?","answer":"Then it shall be, when he lies down, that you shall notice the place where he lies;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:4, After she noticed where Boaz was lying down, what two things was she supposed to do after that? (2 Points)","answer":"and you shall go in, uncover his feet, and lie down;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:4, After Boaz wakes up from having his feet uncovered, what was supposed to happen next?","answer":"and he will tell you what you should do.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:5, Did Ruth agree to the plan Naomi proposed?","answer":"And she said to her, \u201cAll that you say to me I will do.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:6, Where did Ruth go that evening?","answer":"So she went down to the threshing floor and did according to all that her mother-in-law instructed her."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:7, After Boaz did what two things, was his heart cheerful? (2 points)","answer":"And after Boaz had eaten and drunk, and his heart was cheerful,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:7, After Boaz had eaten and drunk, how was he feeling?","answer":"And after Boaz had eaten and drunk, and his heart was cheerful,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:7, Where did Boaz get ready to go to sleep?","answer":"he went to lie down at the end of the heap of grain;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:7, What three things did Ruth do after Boaz had eaten and drunk at the threshing floor that evening?","answer":"and she came softly, uncovered his feet, and lay down."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:8, When did Boaz get startled?","answer":"Now it happened at midnight that the man was startled,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:8, What happened at midnight?","answer":"Now it happened at midnight that the man was startled,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:8, What did Boaz do after he was startled?","answer":"and turned himself;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:8, What did Boaz find in the middle of the night?","answer":"and there, a woman was lying at his feet."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:9, What did Boaz ask the woman at his feet?","answer":"And he said, \u201cWho are you?\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:9, Who was the woman at Boaz' feet?","answer":"So she answered, \u201cI am Ruth, your maidservant."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:9, What did Ruth ask Boaz to do?","answer":"Take your maidservant under your wing,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:9, Why was Ruth asking Boaz to marry her?","answer":"for you are a close relative.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:10, Was Boaz happy Ruth had asked if he would marry her?","answer":"Then he said, \u201cBlessed are you of the Lord, my daughter!"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:10, When did Boaz think Ruth had shown more kindness--at the beginning or at the end?","answer":"For you have shown more kindness at the end than at the beginning,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:10, How had Ruth shown more kindness to Boaz at the end than at the beginning?","answer":"in that you did not go after young men,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:10, What two types of younger men could Ruth have gone after, other than Boaz?","answer":"whether poor or rich."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:11, Did Boaz accept Ruth's proposal?","answer":"And now, my daughter, do not fear. I will do for you all that you request,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:11, What helped Boaz decide if he would marry Ruth or not?","answer":"for all the people of my town know that you are a virtuous woman."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:12, Yes or No?  Did Boaz acknowledge that he was Ruth's close relative?","answer":"Now it is true that I am a close relative;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:12, What problem did Boaz bring up, in why he couldn't marry Ruth?","answer":"however, there is a relative closer than I."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:13, Did Boaz want Ruth to leave the threshing floor?","answer":"Stay this night,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:13, What did Boaz have to do before he could agree to marry Ruth?","answer":"and in the morning it shall be that if he will perform the duty of a close relative for you\u2014good; let him do it."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:13, What was the condition that had to happen, before Boaz could marry Ruth?","answer":"But if he does not want to perform the duty for you,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:13, If the other near relative would not marry Ruth, then what would happen?","answer":"then I will perform the duty for you, as the Lord lives! Lie down until morning.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:14, Where did Ruth spend most of the night?","answer":"So she lay at his feet until morning,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:14, What time was it when Ruth got up to leave?","answer":"and she arose before one could recognize another."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:14, What did Boaz tell Ruth not to tell, when they got up the next morning?","answer":"Then he said, \u201cDo not let it be known that the woman came to the threshing floor.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:15, What did Boaz ask Ruth to hold, while he measured six ephahs of barley into it?","answer":"Also he said, \u201cBring the shawl that is on you and hold it.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:15, How many ephahs of barley did Boaz give to Ruth to take home to Naomi?","answer":"And when she held it, he measured six ephahs of barley, and laid it on her."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:15, After she got the 6 ephahs of barley, where did Ruth go?","answer":"Then she went into the city."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:16, How did Naomi greet Ruth the next morning?","answer":"When she came to her mother-in-law, she said, \u201cIs that you, my daughter?\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:16, When Ruth got home, what did she tell Naomi?","answer":"Then she told her all that the man had done for her."},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:17, How many ephahs of barley had Boaz given Ruth?","answer":"And she said, \u201cThese six ephahs of barley he gave me;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:17, Why had Boaz given Ruth the six ephahs of barley?","answer":"for he said to me, \u2018Do not go empty-handed to your mother-in-law.\u2019 \u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:18, What did Naomi tell Ruth to do that day?","answer":"Then she said, \u201cSit still, my daughter, until you know how the matter will turn out;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 3:18, What did Naomi think Boaz would do that day?","answer":"for the man will not rest until he has concluded the matter this day.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:1, Where did Boaz go the next morning?","answer":"Now Boaz went up to the gate and sat down there;"}

        /*
        //
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        */
    ],
    "c4":[
        {"question":"According to Ruth 4:1, Where did Boaz go the next morning?","answer":"Now Boaz went up to the gate and sat down there;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:1, Who came in through the city gate while Boaz was sitting there?","answer":"and behold, the close relative of whom Boaz had spoken came by."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:1, What did Boaz ask the close relative to do, after he saw him come by?","answer":"So Boaz said, \u201cCome aside, friend, sit down here.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:1, Yes or no?  Did the close relative take the time to talk to Boaz that day?","answer":"So he came aside and sat down."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:2, How many other men did Boaz ask to sit down with him and the close relative?","answer":"And he took ten men of the elders of the city, and said, \u201cSit down here.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:2, Yes or No?  Did the 10 men that Boaz asked to sit down with him agree to do it?","answer":"So they sat down."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:3, To whom was Boaz talking, when he said that Naomi had sold a piece of land?","answer":"Then he said to the close relative,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:3, Who had sold a piece of property?","answer":"\u201cNaomi, who has come back from the country of Moab,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:3, From which country had Naomi come back?","answer":"\u201cNaomi, who has come back from the country of Moab,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:3, What had Naomi done, that Boaz told the close relative?","answer":"sold the piece of land which belonged to our brother Elimelech."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:4, What did Boaz ask the close relative if he wanted to do?","answer":"And I thought to inform you, saying, \u2018Buy it back in the presence of the inhabitants and the elders of my people."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:4, Who would be the witnesses to the land deal, if the near kinsman bought Naomi's land back?","answer":"And I thought to inform you, saying, \u2018Buy it back in the presence of the inhabitants and the elders of my people."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:4, What did Boaz offer for the close relative to do for Naomi's property?","answer":"If you will redeem it, redeem it;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:4, What did Boaz want the close relative to do if he was not going to buy Naomi's property back?","answer":"but if you will not redeem it, then tell me, that I may know;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:4, Was there anyone else who could redeem Naomi's property besides Boaz and this close relative?","answer":"for there is no one but you to redeem it, and I am next after you.\u2019 \u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:4, Did the close relative want to buy back Naomi's land?","answer":"And he said, \u201cI will redeem it.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:5, Boaz told the relative he had to buy the property from Ruth when he did what?","answer":"Then Boaz said, \u201cOn the day you buy the field from the hand of Naomi,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:5, Boaz told the relative when he bought the property from Naomi, he was also buying it from whom?","answer":"you must also buy it from Ruth the Moabitess,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:5, was Ruth a widow?","answer":"the wife of the dead,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:5, What other responsibility did this relative have to Ruth, if he bought the field from Naomi?","answer":"to perpetuate the name of the dead through his inheritance.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:6, After the relative heard he had to marry Ruth and produce an heir for her, did he go ahead with the deal?","answer":"And the close relative said, \u201cI cannot redeem it for myself, lest I ruin my own inheritance."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:6, Whom did the relative say should redeem the property, since he changed his mind?","answer":"You redeem my right of redemption for yourself, for I cannot redeem it.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:7, why would people give each other a shoe in former times in Israel?","answer":"Now this was the custom in former times in Israel concerning redeeming and exchanging, to confirm anything:"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:7, What was the custom in former times in Israel concerning redeeming and exchanging anything?","answer":"one man took off his sandal and gave it to the other,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:7, the exchange of a shoe in ancient Israel after making a deal would serve as what in Israel in old times?","answer":"and this was a confirmation in Israel."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:8, The close relative told Boaz to do what?","answer":"Therefore the close relative said to Boaz, \u201cBuy it for yourself.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:8,  What did the close relative do to show he was giving up his right to buy the field?","answer":"So he took off his sandal."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:9, Who were the witnesses to Boaz buying all of Elimelech's possessions from Naomi?","answer":"And Boaz said to the elders and all the people,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:9, Whose property had Boaz bought, in addition to all that was Chilion's and Mahlon's that day?","answer":"\u201cYou are witnesses this day that I have bought all that was Elimelech\u2019s,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:9, Whose other two men's property had Boaz bought that day, in addition to all that wasy Elimelech's?","answer":"and all that was Chilion\u2019s and Mahlon\u2019s,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:9, From whom had Boaz bought all that belonged to Elimelech, Chilion and Mahlon?","answer":"from the hand of Naomi."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:10, Which brother had Ruth married?  Mahlon, or Chilion?","answer":"Moreover, Ruth the Moabitess, the widow of Mahlon,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:10, Whom else had Boaz acquired in the land deal and in what capacity? (2 points)","answer":"I have acquired as my wife,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:10, What was the purpose of Boaz marrying Ruth?","answer":"to perpetuate the name of the dead through his inheritance,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:10, Why would someone be willing to have a child for his dead brother?","answer":"that the name of the dead may not be cut off from among his brethren"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:10, Boaz was willing to have a child for Mahlon, so that his name would not be cut off, and what else?","answer":"and from his position at the gate."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:10, Why had Boaz called the people of the town together that day?","answer":"You are witnesses this day.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:11, Yes or No?  Did the 10 elders agree to be witnesses to Boaz buying everything from Naomi?","answer":"And all the people who were at the gate, and the elders, said, \u201cWe are witnesses."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:11, Which two ladies built the house of Israel?","answer":"The Lord make the woman who is coming to your house like Rachel and Leah,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:11, The witnesses credited Rachel and Leah with doing what?","answer":"the two who built the house of Israel;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:11, What did the townspeople want for Ruth and Boaz in Ephrathah?","answer":"and may you prosper in Ephrathah"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:11, Where did the townspeople want Ruth and Boaz to prosper?","answer":"and may you prosper in Ephrathah"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:11, What did the townspeople want for Ruth and Boaz in Bethlehem?","answer":"and be famous in Bethlehem."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:11, Where did the townspeople want Ruth and Boaz to be famous?","answer":"and be famous in Bethlehem."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:12, The witnesses said they wanted Ruth and Boaz to be like the house of whom, whose parents were Tamar and Judah?","answer":"May your house be like the house of Perez,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:12, Who were Perez's parents? (2 points)","answer":"whom Tamar bore to Judah,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:12, Who were the townspeople blessing, to be like Pharez?","answer":"because of the offspring which the Lord will give you from this young woman.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:13, After Boaz got home from the meeting with the near kinsman, what did Boaz and Ruth do?","answer":"So Boaz took Ruth and she became his wife;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:13, After they were married, did Ruth become pregnant?","answer":"and when he went in to her, the Lord gave her conception,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:13, Did Ruth have a boy or a girl?","answer":"and she bore a son."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:14, After the baby was born, who came to visit Ruth and Naomi?","answer":"Then the women said to Naomi,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:14, What did the women say to Naomi, when they came to visit the baby?","answer":"\u201cBlessed be the Lord, who has not left you this day without a close relative;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:14, The women wanted the baby to be famous where?","answer":"and may his name be famous in Israel!"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:15, What did they hope Obed would be to Naomi? (2 points)","answer":"And may he be to you a restorer of life and a nourisher of your old age;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:15, What nice thing did the women of the town say about Ruth, besides she was better than seven sons?","answer":"for your daughter-in-law, who loves you,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:15, The women of the town said Ruth was better to Naomi than what?","answer":"who is better to you than seven sons,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:15, Did Ruth have a girl or a boy?","answer":"has borne him.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:16, Who was the child's nurse?","answer":"Then Naomi took the child and laid him on her bosom, and became a nurse to him."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:17, Who said, \"There is a son born to Naomi!\".","answer":"Also the neighbor women gave him a name, saying, \u201cThere is a son born to Naomi.\u201d"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:17, Who gave Obed his name?","answer":"And they called his name Obed."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:17, Obed was the father of whom?","answer":"He is the father of Jesse,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:17, Jesse was the father of whom?","answer":"the father of David."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:18, Who is the patriarch of the geneology that we are going to learn in this chapter?  With whom does it start?","answer":"Now this is the genealogy of Perez:"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:18, Who was Perez' son?","answer":"Perez begot Hezron;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:18, Who was Hezron's father?","answer":"Perez begot Hezron;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:19, Who was Hezron's son?","answer":"Hezron begot Ram,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:19, Who was Ram's father?","answer":"Hezron begot Ram,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:19, Who was Ram's son?","answer":"and Ram begot Amminadab;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:19, Who was Amminadab's father?","answer":"and Ram begot Amminadab;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:20, Who was the father of Salmon?","answer":"Amminadab begot Nahshon,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:20, Who was Salmon's father?","answer":"Amminadab begot Nahshon,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:20, Who was the father of Salmon?","answer":"and Nahshon begot Salmon;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:20, Who was Nahshon's son?","answer":"and Nahshon begot Salmon;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:21, Who was the father of Boaz?","answer":"Salmon begot Boaz,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:21, Who was Salmon's son?","answer":"Salmon begot Boaz,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:21, Who was Boaz's son?","answer":"and Boaz begot Obed;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:21, Who was Obed's father?","answer":"and Boaz begot Obed;"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:22, Who is the father of Jesse?","answer":"Obed begot Jesse,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:22, Who is Obed's son?","answer":"Obed begot Jesse,"},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:22, Who was David's father?","answer":"and Jesse begot David."},{"question":"According to Ruth 4:22, Who was Jesse's son?","answer":"and Jesse begot David."}
        
        /*
        //
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        { "question" : "" , "answer" : ""},
        */
    
    ]

}


function ruth_c1(){
    //converts the json object into somthing readable
    //generates a random number over the length of the JSON array
    var i = Math.floor(Math.random()*ruth.c1.length);
    document.getElementById("number").innerHTML = "Question #" + (i+1);
    //puts the random question into the html
    document.getElementById("question").innerHTML =
    ruth.c1[i].question;
    //puts the correct random answer into the html
    document.getElementById("answer").innerHTML =
    "<b>"+" Correct Answer:" + "<br>"+ "</b>"+
    ruth.c1[i].answer;
    //hides the answer
    document.getElementById("answer").style.display = "none";
    //changes the button back 
    document.getElementById("show").innerHTML ="Show Answer";
    //erases user text
    document.getElementById("u_answer").value = "";
}

function ruth_c2(){
    //converts the json object into somthing readable
    //generates a random number over the length of the JSON array
    var i = Math.floor(Math.random()*ruth.c2.length);
    document.getElementById("number").innerHTML = "Question #" + (i+1);
    //puts the random question into the html
    document.getElementById("question").innerHTML =
    ruth.c2[i].question;
    //puts the correct random answer into the html
    document.getElementById("answer").innerHTML =
    "<b>"+" Correct Answer:" + "<br>"+ "</b>"+
    ruth.c2[i].answer;
    //hides the answer
    document.getElementById("answer").style.display = "none";
    //changes the button back 
    document.getElementById("show").innerHTML ="Show Answer";
    //erases user text
    document.getElementById("u_answer").value = "";
}

function ruth_c3(){
    //converts the json object into somthing readable
    //generates a random number over the length of the JSON array
    var i = Math.floor(Math.random()*ruth.c3.length);
    document.getElementById("number").innerHTML = "Question #" + (i+1);
    //puts the random question into the html
    document.getElementById("question").innerHTML =
    ruth.c3[i].question;
    //puts the correct random answer into the html
    document.getElementById("answer").innerHTML =
    "<b>"+" Correct Answer:" + "<br>"+ "</b>"+
    ruth.c3[i].answer;
    //hides the answer
    document.getElementById("answer").style.display = "none";
    //changes the button back 
    document.getElementById("show").innerHTML ="Show Answer";
    //erases user text
    document.getElementById("u_answer").value = "";
}

function ruth_c4(){
    //converts the json object into somthing readable
    //generates a random number over the length of the JSON array
    var i = Math.floor(Math.random()*ruth.c4.length);
    document.getElementById("number").innerHTML = "Question #" + (i+1);
    //puts the random question into the html
    document.getElementById("question").innerHTML =
    ruth.c4[i].question;
    //puts the correct random answer into the html
    document.getElementById("answer").innerHTML =
    "<b>"+" Correct Answer:" + "<br>"+ "</b>"+
    ruth.c4[i].answer;
    //hides the answer
    document.getElementById("answer").style.display = "none";
    //changes the button back 
    document.getElementById("show").innerHTML ="Show Answer";
    //erases user text
    document.getElementById("u_answer").value = "";
}